<?xml version="1.0"?>
<page title="Fakemail documentation" here="Fakemail">
    <long_title>
        Fakemail is a SMTP gateway replacement to make mail testing easier
    </long_title>
    <content>
        <section name="what" title="What is fakemail?">
            <p>
                Fakemail is a dummy SMTP gateway written in Perl.
                It's a tool for testing applications that works by acting
                as an intercept for outgoing mails.
            </p>
            <p>
                If you have had to test applications that send e-mails, for
                example as part of a web sign up process, you will know what
                an involved and tricky exercise that can be.
                Usually you have to sign up with a special e-mail address,
                have the mail go to the mail server and then real it back into
                the test with a POP/IMAP client.
                Besides all of the extra POP libraries you need there is also
                the spurious failures because of mail delays and the difficulty
                of setting all of this up for every development box.
                That's assuming you get all of the developer machines past
                the security that should be protecting your mail server.
            </p>
            <p>
                Fakemail works by intercepting the mail before it leaves
                the machine by replacing your mail transfer agent (MTA).
                It's a simple script run from the command line and then
                killed when it's captured the mails...
<sh>
fakemail --host=localhost --port=10025 path=temp --background
</sh>
                Mails are simply dumped to a directory of your choosing,
                here the a temporary directory, complete with all of mail headers.
                Briefly, the port parameter is the port to listen on initially,
                the host parameter is not currently checked and
                the background flag tells <em>fakemail</em> to run as a
                daemon and to return the process ID of the detached process.
            </p>
            <p>
                If you already have an SMTP server on your computer, then you
                will either need to disable it to free up port 25 or use
                another port.
                The second option means that your mail sending library must have the
                capability to select a port other than 25 by some sort of
                configuration.
            </p>
        </section>
        <section name="install" title="Basic installation">
            <p>
                There is no installation of the fakemail program itself, but
                it does have some prerequisites.
                The first is <a href="http://www.perl.org/">Perl</a> itself and
                beyond the basic distribution you will also need the
                <a href="http://cpan.perl.org">CPAN</a>
                module <em>Net::Server::Mail::SMTP</em>.
                Once Perl is installed you can install this module with...
<sh>
perl -MCPAN -e 'install Net::Server::Mail::SMTP'
</sh>
                For <em>fakemail</em> itself all you have to do is unpack the
                <a href="http://sourceforge.net/projects/fakemail/">Sourceforge</a>
                tarball and it's ready to run.
            </p>
            <p>
                To confirm everything is working, we should send it an e-mail.
                Open a terminal and start <em>fakemail</em> in the foreground...
<sh>
fakemail --host=localhost --port=10025 path=.
</sh>
                All of these arguments are required.
                Here is what they mean:
                <ul>
                    <li>
                        The host parameter names the server as <em>localhost</em>.
                        Although required, thisis not yet acted upon.
                    </li>
                    <li>
                        The port argument sets the port that <em>fakemail</em>
                        will listen on for connections.
                        It will listen on this port until it's process is killed.
                        <em>fakemail</em> is a full INET server and can handle
                        multiple simultaneous requests.
                        Note you can only connect to ports below 1024 if you
                        are the root user.
                    </li>
                    <li>
                        The path is the directory where the captured mails will
                        be saved.
                        The name of the file is the &quot;to&quot; address of
                        the incoming mail with the index appended.
                        For example the second mail sent to &quot;me@here&quot;
                        will be saved in the file &quot;me@here.2&quot;
                    </li>
                </ul>
                That terminal is now occupied, so open another and connect with
                <em>telnet</em> to the port we chose earlier...
<sh>
telnet localhost 10025
</sh>
                If everything is working we should see the response...
<sh>
Connected to localhost.localdomain (127.0.0.1).
Escape character is '^]'.
220 uno.home SMTP Net::Server::Mail (Perl) Service ready
</sh>
                We can manually enter SMTP commands to simulate a mail dispatch,
                although we have to send them in order.
                The commands are &quot;HELO&quot; to start the session,
                &quot;MAIL From:&quot; to set the sender, &quot;RCPT To:&quot;
                to set the target and &quot;DATA&quot; for the mail content
                itself.
                The &quot;QUIT&quot; command ends the session.
                Here is the full conversation with our commands in bold...
<sh><![CDATA[
220 uno.home SMTP Net::Server::Mail (Perl) Service ready
<strong>HELO mailer</strong>
250 Requested mail action okay, completed
<strong>MAIL From: me@here</strong>
250 sender me@here OK
<strong>RCPT To: you@there</strong>
250 recipient you@there OK
<strong>DATA</strong>
354 Start mail input; end with <CRLF>.<CRLF>
<strong>
A-header: Sample header

Hello
.</strong>
250 message queued
<strong>QUIT</strong>
221 uno.home Service closing transmission channel
]]></sh>
                We must enter both a carriage return and a line feed for
                each mail header line, although most <em>telnet</em> programs
                will do that automatically.
            </p>
            <p>
                After this sequence we can stop the fakemail terminal with
                a Control-C to interrupt the process.
                Because we set the <em>fakemail</em> path to the local directory,
                we should see a file labelled &quot;you@there.1&quot;.
                Here is the contents of that file...
<pre>
A-header: Sample header

Hello
</pre>
                You should now be ready to use <em>fakemail</em> to make your
                testing easier.
            </p>
        </section>
        <section name="typical" title="A typical test case">
            <p>
                I am going to use a <a href="http://www.simpletest.org/">SimpleTest</a>
                (PHP) example here, but translation to
                <a href="http://sourceforge.net/projects/jwebunit">JWebUnit</a>
                or <a href="http://sourceforge.net/projects/htmlunit">HtmlUnit</a>
                should be straight forward.
            </p>
            <p>
                Firstly we will need a web page to test...
<php><![CDATA[
<html>
    <?php
        require_once('class.phpmailer.php');
        
        if (isset($_GET['email'])) {
            $mail = new PHPMailer();
            $mail->from = 'test@lastcraft.com';
            $mail->body = 'Hello';
            $mail->host = 'localhost';
            $mail->mailer = 'smtp';
            $mail->port = isset($_GET['port']) ? $_GET['port'] : 25;
            if ($mail->send()) {
                print 'Mail sent to <em>' . $_GET['email'] . '</em><br />';
            }
        }
    ?>
    <form>
        Enter your mail address:<br />
        <input type=text name="email" /><br />
        <input type="submit" value="Send" />
    </form>
</html>
]]></php>
                This is not strictly test driven develoment of course, but things
                are easier to explain this way.
            </p>
            <p>
                Because the inbuilt PHP <code>mail()</code> function does not
                let you override the port, I am using the
                <a href="http://sourceforge.net/projects/phpmailer/">PHPMailer library</a>.
                This library has it's own SMTP client making the choice of port
                easy to configure.
                I am taking the port as an extra form parameter,
                because we don't always have the freedom to disable mail transfer
                agents whilst testing.
            </p>
            <p>
                Now the test case...
<php><![CDATA[
<?php
    class MailGreetingTest extends WebTestCase {
    
        function setUp() {
            $command = 'fakemail --path=temp --host=localhost --port=10025';
            $this->pid = `$command`;
            @unlink('temp/marcus@lastcraft.com.1');
        }
        
        function tearDown() {
            $command = 'kill ' . $this->pid;
            `$command`;
            @unlink('temp/marcus@lastcraft.com.1');
        }
        
        function testGreetingMailIsSent() {
            $this->get('http://my-host/mail.php');
            $this->setField('email', 'marcus@lastcraft.com');
            $this->clickSubmit('Send', array('port' => 10025));
            $this->assertWantedText('mail sent to marcus@lastcraft.com');
            
            $sent = file_get_contents('temp/marcus@lastcraft.com.1');
            list($headers, $content) = split("\r\n\r\n", $sent);
            $this->assertTrue(trim($content) == 'Hello');
        }
    }
?>
]]></php>
                The main point of course is that <em>fakemail</em> is started
                and stopped for each test using <code>setUp()</code> and
                <code>tearDown()</code>.
                In addition to keeping track of the process ID so as to
                kill <em>fakemail</em> after each test, we also need to delete
                the captured mails.
                Otherwise the next mail will be saved as <em>marcus@lastcraft.com.2</em>
                making our tests a erratic.
            </p>
            <p>
                The only tricky bit in the test is the <code>clickSubmit()</code>
                line.
                That's where we send the extra port parameter override for
                testing so that the mail is sent to <em>fakemail</em> rather
                than the regular mail transfer agent.
            </p>
            <p>
                The actual test itself could be improved by some obvious refactoring.
                Creating a generic <code>MailTestCase</code> would involve
                more useful assertions such as <code>assertMailText()</code>
                and <code>clickMailLink()</code> for testing double opt-ins.
                For ease of illustration, I am just picking the captured mail
                apart to confirm the not very exciting content.
                Hopefully your own tests will be much more interesting.
            </p>
        </section>
    </content>
    <internal>
        <link>
            <a href="#what">What is fakemail?</a>
        </link>
        <link>
            <a href="#install">Installing</a> and testing the installation.
        </link>
        <link>
            A <a href="#typical">Typical test case</a> using fakemail.
        </link>
    </internal>
    <external>
        <link>
        </link>
    </external>
    <meta>
        <keywords>
        </keywords>
    </meta>
</page>